Finding Aid for Josselyn Van Tyne papers, 1917-1958
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Josselyn Van Tyne papers 1917-1958
Van Tyne, Josselyn, 1902-1957.
(in 5 boxes)
3 linear feet
86175 Aa 2
Ornithologist and curator of birds in the Museum of Zoology, and professor of zoology at University of Michigan. Correspondence and other papers concerning his interest in birds, his activities with the Wilson Ornithological Club, and his scientific expeditions to Indochina and British Honduras in the late Twenties; and papers on student life at Harvard University, 1922-1925; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Helen Bates Van Tyne (donor 715 ), widow of Josselyn Van Tyne, in 1971.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Josselyn Van Tyne was born on May 11, 1902 in Philadelphia, PA. Following graduation from Culver Military Academy, he received his AB degree from Harvard University in 1925 and his doctor of philosophy degree from the University of Michigan in 1928. That same year he joined the U-M faculty as assistant curator in the Museum of Zoology. In 1931, he became curator of birds. Van Tyne also taught, serving as assistant professor of zoology between 1937 and 1948, as associate professor from 1948 to 1954, and as full professor since 1954.
In 1954, he served as president of the ecology section of the International Ornithological Congress in Basel, Switzerland. He was president of the American Ornithologists' Union from 1950 to 1953. In addition, he was a member of various professional societies, including the University of Michigan Research Club; British Ornithologists' Club, Cranbrook Institute of Science, where he was a trustee, and the International Ornithological Congresses Committee. Josselyn Van Tyne died Jan. 30, 1957.
The Josselyn Van Tyne papers consist of correspondence and other papers concerning his interest in birds, his activities with the Wilson Ornithological Club, and his scientific expeditions to Indochina and British Honduras in the late Twenties; and papers on student life at Harvard University, 1922-1925 and photographs. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Other Materials; and Photographs. Correspondents in the collection include Thomas Barbour, Alfred B. Connable, Harold J. Coolidge, Lee R. Dice, Frederick M. Gaige, Harry G. Kipke, David Rockefeller, and Norman A. Wood.
The Photographs are of scientific expeditions to Indochina (1928-1930), Texas (1928-1935), British Honduras and Guatemala (1931), Yucatan, Mexico (1936), and Bylot Island, Northwest Territories, Canada (1950s). The photos include local populations and scenery as well as activities of expedition members. The Guatemala and Yucatan expeditions files contain photos of Mayan ruins, especially Chichén Itzá.
Subjects:
Belize.; Birds.; Harvard University.; Indochina.; Scientific expeditions.; Students--Massachusetts--Cambridge.; Tonkin.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Zoology.; Van Tyne, Josselyn, 1902-1957.; Wilson Ornithological Club.; Zoology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Archaeological sites--Yucatán Peninsula.; Belize--Description and travel--Photographs.; Boats--Indochina.; Bylot Island (Nunavut)--Description and travel--Photographs.; Canada.; Chichén Itzá Site (Mexico)--Description and travel--Photographs.; Dogsleds.; Eskimos.; Expeditions and surveys.; Guatemala--Description and travel--Photographs.; Indians of North America--Canada.; Indochina--Description and travel--Photographs.; Laos.; Mexico--Description and travel--Photographs.; Texas--Description and travel--Photographs.; Tonkin.; Yucatán Peninsula--Description and travel--Photographs.; Zoology.
Contributors:
Barbour, Thomas, 1884-1946.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-; Coolidge, Harold J. (Harold Jefferson), 1904-1985; Darlington, Philip Jackson, 1904-1983.; Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.; Gaige, Frederick M.; Kipke, Harry G., 1899-1972.; Rockefeller, David, 1915-; Wheeler, Ralph Emerson, 1901-; Wood, Norman Asa, 1857-
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1917-1935, 31 folders (Box 1)
  - 1936-1956, 12 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Newspaper clippings 1929-1956 (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning scientific expedition to Indochina 1928-1930, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets concerning the annual meetings of scientific groups 1923-1953 (Box 2)
  - Biographical material 1939-1957 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers of Mrs. C.H. Van Tyne 1894-1945 (Box 2)
  - Articles (Box 2)
  - Notebook concerning birds sighted by Van Tyne 1917-1919 (Box 2)
  - Journal concerning scientific activities 1938-1943 (Box 2)
  - Roll Call, 1920, yearbook of Culver Military Academy (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - British Honduras and Guatemala 1931 (Box 3)
    (loose items from album)
  - Bylot Island, Northwest Territories, Canada 1950s
    (some photos used in Spring on an Arctic Island, by Katharine Scherman)
    - Dog sledding (Box 3)
    - Expedition members (Box 3)
    - People (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Indochina 1928-1930
    - Expedition members (Box 3)
    - Hue (Box 3)
    - Loose items from album (Box 3)
    - People (Box 3)
    - River travel (Box 3)
    - Village activities (Box 3)
    - Villages (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Texas 1928-1935 loose items from album (Box 3)
  - Yucatan, Mexico 1936
    - Chichen-Itza ruins (photos) (Box 3)
    - Chichen-Itza ruins (postcards) (Box 3)
    - Countryside scenes (Box 3)
    - Expedition members (Box 3)
    - Merida (Box 3)
    - Uxmal ruins (postcards) (Box 3)
    - Village and town scenes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Glass slides of Indo-China scenes, in small box; most identifications were taken off the slides
    - [aerial view of village] (Box 3)
    - Indo-China, Expedition, Unknown Member (Box 3)
    - Cambodia, Phnom Penh July 1929 (Box 3)
    - [horses-work] (Box 3)
    - [landscape]
      - General (Box 3)
      - Cave (Box 3)
      - Natives in the distance (Box 3)
      - Natives, village (Box 3)
      - River rafting, 6 slides (Box 3)
      - Tent (Box 3)
      - Trees, grass (Box 3)
      - Water, mountains, 2 slides (Box 3)
      - Water, trees (Box 3)
      - Work animals on trail (Box 3)
    - Laos
      - Banten Khaen
        - Palm Frond June 11, 1929 (Box 3)
        - Palm & Nest June 11, 1929 (Box 3)
      - Luang Prabang June 14, 1929, 4 slides (Box 3)
      - Luang Prabang, King Sisavang Vong (Box 3)
      - Mekong River, Raft on June 1929, 3 slides (Box 3)
      - Nam Hou River, on the June 1929, 5 slides (Box 3)
      - Nam Hou River, Cliff Near June 1929 (Box 3)
      - Nest Tree... June 11, 1929 (Box 3)
      - Phongsaly May 1929 (Box 3)
    - Letter from King of Luang Prabang June 1929 (Box 3)
    - [man with backpack] (Box 3)
    - [man with box] (Box 3)
    - [man with young woman] (Box 3)
    - [man riding large animal] (Box 3)
    - [men, FME] (Box 3)
    - [men with horses] (Box 3)
    - [men on raft] (Box 3)
    - Map of Burma, Siam & French Indo-China
      - Black & White (Box 3)
      - Color (Box 3)
    - Map of Burma, Siam, China, Black & White, 2 slides (Box 3)
    - [statues] (Box 3)
    - Tonkin
      - Lai Chau March 1929
        - General, 2 slides (Box 3)
        - Mafu, near (Box 3)
        - Meo Hunter, 2 slides (Box 3)
      - Lao Kay February 10, 1929 (Box 3)
      - Muong Moun March 1929
        - General (Box 3)
        - On the road to (Box 3)
        - Thai Children
      - Northern, Native Pack Saddle March 1929 (Box 3)
      - Pattam, near March 9, 1929 (Box 3)
      - Phong Tho
        - February 22, 1929, 2 slides (Box 3)
        - 12 km east of February 22, 1929 (Box 3)
      - Pou Den Dinh April 17, 1929, 2 slides (Box 3)
    - Trap Line (Box 3)
    - Vientiane July 1929, 4 slides (Box 3)
    - [woman] (Box 3)
    - [woman with animal] (Box 3)
    - [woman with child] (Box 3)
    - [woman, weaving] (Box 3)
    - [woman working] (Box 3)
    - [women in costume] (Box 3)
    - [young girls] (Box 3)
    - [young men], 2 slides (Box 3)
    - [young woman] (Box 3)
  - Album of scientific expedition to British Honduras and Guatemala, 1931 (Box 4)
    (includes photos of scenery, expedition activities, Mayan ruins; album also includes photos, 1928-1935, of travels in Texas)
  - Album of scientific expedition to Indochina, 1928-1930 (Box 4)
    (includes photos of scenery, agricultural and village activities, expedition members, people in folk costumes)
- Later materials 1947-1958, 3 folders (Box 5)
  (Files relating to writing and posthumous publication of his book, Fundamentals of Ornithology)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Barbour, Thomas, 1884-1946.
1925, 1930-1933, 1938-1939, 1943, 1945
Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-
1941-1950, 1954-1956
Coolidge, Harold J. (Harold Jefferson), 1904-
1928-1933, 1948
Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.
1923-1924, April 13, 1925
Gaige, Frederick M.
1926-1935, 1937-1940, 1945
Kipke, Harry G., 1899-1972.
1939-1942
Rockefeller, David, 1915-
1955-1956
Wood, Norman Asa, 1857-
1924-1931